<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Due right of tithes examined: in a letter from a gentleman to his friend, wherein is proved that Jesus Christ did not work as a carpenter, nor did ever command his Apostles or ministers to work for a livelihood: by way of answer to some passages in Mr. Fishers Baby-baptism. By an aged gentleman, who cannot long expect to have the comfort of ministers of their ministery.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81789</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2441</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E714_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207243</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866308</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866308</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118577</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81789)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118577)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 110:E714[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Due right of tithes examined: in a letter from a gentleman to his friend, wherein is proved that Jesus Christ did not work as a carpenter, nor did ever command his Apostles or ministers to work for a livelihood: by way of answer to some passages in Mr. Fishers Baby-baptism. By an aged gentleman, who cannot long expect to have the comfort of ministers of their ministery.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Pierrepont, and are to be sold at the Sun in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654. [i.e. 1653]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob. 8"; the 4 in imprint date has been crossed out and date altered to 1653.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tithes --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118577:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DVE RIGHT OF TITHES <hi>EXAMINED:</hi> In a LETTER from a Gentleman to his friend, wherein is proved that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> did not work as a Carpenter, nor did ever command his Apoſtles or Miniſters to work for a livelihood: By way of anſwer to ſome paſſages in Mr. <hi>Fiſhers Baby-Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By an aged Gentleman, who cannot long expect to have the comfort of Miniſters or their Miniſtery.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mal. 3.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Bring ye all the Tithes into the ſtorehouſe, that there may be meat in mine houſe, and prove me now herewith, ſaith the <hi>Lord</hi> of Hoſts, if I will not open you the windows of heaven, and pour you out a bleſſing.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of sun</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Pierrepont,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Sun in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118577:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118577:2"/>
            <head>A Copie of a Letter from a Friend.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oving friend, amongſt the many thoughts which theſe times doth cauſe within me, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doth ſo much tronble me, as that the Adverſary of mankinde, who transformeth himſelf into an Angel of light, thereby even to deceive the Elect of the Lord, if it were poſſible: who hath ſtirred up, in my apprehenſion, many men of parrs and gifts, to ſet themſelves againſt a ſetled and conſtant Miniſtery, which God and Chriſt Jeſus hath appointed and promiſed unto his Church and people, for to teach them to obſerve and do all things whatſoever I have commanded you, and ſaid, <hi>Lo, I am with you alway, even to the end of the world, Matth.</hi> 28.20. And this hath lately been attempted, by pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioning to the Supreme Power now in being, for the taking away of all means and maintenance from thoſe they call Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters: hoping thereby to deſtroy and put down that Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, which I am perſwaded the Lord himſelf did firſt inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute and ordain: And will continue and uphold it, even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end: notwithſtanding all their machinations and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118577:3"/>for I am given to underſtand, they are confident that if they can prevail, to have all the means taken from them, whereby they may have a livelihood, that the Miniſtery will fall of it ſelf, that then all gifted men may exerciſe themſelves in their places, at pleaſure, which being but duly conſidered of all ſuch as truly fear the Lord, though themſelves at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent do not, what woful diſtractions and diviſions will follow thereupon, my heart even trembleth to think on: for if once Maintenance and Encouragement be taken from the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, and every man ſuffered to teach what himſelf pleaſeth and approveth of, then may not men teach Atheiſme, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſm, Turciſm, Judaiſme, Arrianiſme, Libertimſme, Idol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhipping, &amp; what elſe mans corrupt and ſenſual wils may prompt them unto? and vvill not thereby be a fair opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity given vvith liberty for Jeſuites and all Sectaries calling themſelves gifted men, for to draw Diſciples after them, and alſo thereby making men to be factious, and cauſing diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons amongſt the people: cauſing thereby diſturbances to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, whereby it may be feared, but little peace will follow ſuch courſes? For how can the Lord give a bleſſing to ſuch diſordered doings? for God is not the Authour of confuſion, but of peace: And the Lord never appointed, but one order &amp; worſhip to his Church &amp; people, at one time, as the whole Scripture teſtifieth; and that the Lord would have men to beſtow in his ſervice ſuch temporal things, as he had freely given unto them for their uſe and ſuſtentation; wherefore the Lord himſelf commanded and taught his people at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, even before he appointed a Miniſtery or Miniſters, for to offer Sacrifices unto him of thoſe clean beaſts and fruits of the earth which he had given unto them, thereby to manifeſt themſelves his ſervants, and to ſhew forth their faith and obedience unto him their great <hi>Jehovah</hi> and Creatour: as <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.3, 4. and 8.20. Alſo <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob</hi> and the reſt of the Patriarchs offered Sacrifices to the Lord, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, long before they became a Nation or Common-weal; but after that they were multiplied &amp; grown by the bleſſing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118577:3"/>and promiſe of the Lord made unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> that his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſhould be a great people and Nation, which was accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed in <hi>Egypt,</hi> from whence the Lord brought and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them by his great and mighty power: Now the Lord ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving brought them forth by the conduct of his faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <hi>Moſes,</hi> from out of <hi>Egype</hi> to the Mount <hi>Sinai, Exod.</hi> 19. <hi>And the Lord came down upon the Mount Sinai, on the top of the Mount. And the Lord called Moſes up to the top of the Mount; and Moſes went up.</hi> And unto <hi>Moſes</hi> the Lord delivered his Law, the ten Commandements, which are to be kept by all people, with the Ceremonial Law appertaining to the <hi>Jews:</hi> And alſo appointed and commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> to make a Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, with all the utenſils thereof, and the manner of the Sacrifices and offerings which the people were to offer, and to give out of their own proper goods and eſtates for the maintenance of the Tabernacle, and alſo the Tithes, with part of the offerings, and fourty eight Cities with their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs, which the Lord gave and appointed for the Prieſts and Levites for the maintenance and ſubſiſtance of them and theirs. Now if that order and Prieſthood of <hi>Aaron,</hi> which was to be aboliſhed had ſuch great maintenance, then ſhall not that order of Miniſters, which our High Prieſt Chriſt Jeſus hath ſet up, and appointed over his Church and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, have likewiſe means and ſubſiſtence provided for them and theirs in as great a meaſure, they being Miniſters under Jeſus Chriſt of his Goſpel, which is far more glorious then that of the Law? And therefore to be provided for, as the Goſpel teacheth, notwithſtanding the clamours and petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt it by divers, who profeſs the fear of the Lord, and ſeeming to be very forward promoters of the worſhip of God in the purity thereof: but I fear their zeal is not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to knowledge, but for their own ends, and to ſet up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: no, nor yet the Goſpel-way: and let ſuch men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare or ſhew from Scripture, where ever Chriſt commanded that his Apoſtles, Diſciples, or Miniſters ought not or ſhould not be provided for with means and mainteance, if they can:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118577:4"/>or that Chriſt ever appointed, or commanded them, to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain themſelves by their own labours or occupations, or that Chriſt Jeſus himſelf ever wrought as a Carpenter. And let all ſuch blinde zealous perſons take notice what Chriſt Jeſus him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſaid and did, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.18, 19, 20. and <hi>Mark</hi> 1.17, 18. where Chriſt called <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Andrew:</hi> and ſaid unto them, <hi>Follow me, and I will make you fiſhers of men; and they followed him:</hi> And can thoſe Zelotes finde in Scripture, that ever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that they uſed the trade of fiſhing for the maintenance of themſelves and theirs, but followed their Miniſteriall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice or Calling, Preaching and ſaying, <hi>The Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is at hand.</hi> And likewiſe will it not plainly appear to all men, except wilfully blinde, that the Apoſtles &amp; Miniſters of Chriſt Jeſus ought to be provided for by thoſe to whom they preached, as is evident by Chriſt Jeſus his manner of ſending them forth to preach the Goſpel? <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.7, 8, 9, 10. and <hi>Luke</hi> 10.3, 4, 5, 6, 7. <hi>For the labourer is worthy of his hire:</hi> or did Chriſt ever forbid tithes to be paid to the Phariſees, which was for their maintenance, but approved thereof? for doth not Chriſt ſay, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.42. <hi>For ye tithe Mint and Rue, and all manner of herbs, and paſs over judgement and the love of God; theſe ought you to have done: and not to leave the other un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> where they may obſerve how our Lord Jeſus Chriſt reproved the Phariſees for their paſſing over judgement and the love of God, wherein they ſhould have inſtructed the people, but not for their tithing thoſe ſmall things, which lawfully they might, but in ſubordination to the weightier matters of the Law; neither can thoſe men who are ſo earneſt to have all Maintenance taken from Miniſters, ſhew that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſt Jeſus or his Apoſtles and Miniſters have any where in Scripture forbidden their ſucceſſors and followers, either the taking of Tithes, or other Maintenance for to be allowed unto them: Nay, may it not be ſaid unto thoſe men, that Chriſt Jeſus received Tithes? The reaſon, for that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham gave Tithes unto Melchiſedeck of all, Gen.</hi> 14. which was long before the Lord appointed them to be given unto <hi>Aaron</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118577:4"/>&amp; his ſucceſſors: for Chriſt Jeſus was not an High Prieſt after the order of <hi>Aaron,</hi> but of <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> unto whom <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> gave a tenth part of all, of whom it is ſaid <hi>without father, without mother, without deſcent, having neither beginning of dayes nor end of life, but made like the Son of God, abideth a Prieſt continually:</hi> and in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>0. and <hi>Heb</hi> 7. <hi>The Lord hath ſworn and will not repent, Thou art a Prieſt for ſever after the order of Melchiſedeck.</hi> Now for that it plainly appeareth that <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> was a Prieſt, figure and type of Chriſt Jeſus; And his Prieſthood, unto whom tithes were paid by <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> the father of all the faithful; Let thoſe Zelots from Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture prove that neither tithes nor other maintenance ought to be given unto the ſucceſſours of Chriſt Jeſus, but that they ought to labour, working with their own hands for a livelihood, as thoſe men ſay: but I affirm, that I never read, neither ſhall thoſe men ever in Scripture read, that although Chriſt Jeſus, our Lord and Saviour, was called, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.55. <hi>Is not this the Carpenters ſon? Is not his mother called</hi> Mary? and <hi>Mark</hi> 6.3. <hi>Is not this the Carpenter, the Son of Mary?</hi> but yet that he ever wrought as a Carpenter, the Scripture no where teſtifieth, but the Scripture ſaith, <hi>That at twelve yeeres of age he was found in the Temple, ſitting in the midſt of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, both hearing them and asking them queſtions, Luke</hi> 2.42.46, &amp; 48. <hi>And his mother ſaid unto him, Son why haſt thou thus dealt with us? Behold, thy father and I have ſought thee ſorrowing.</hi> Now will any man but a blinde one from theſe words of <hi>Mary</hi> ſay, that <hi>Joſeph</hi> her husband was Chriſts father? I believe not: but heare Chriſt his anſwer, <hi>Verſe</hi> 49. <hi>And he ſaid unto them, How is it that ye ſought me? wiſt ye not that I muſt be about my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers buſineſs? and they underſtood not the ſaying.</hi> Now if Chriſt Jeſus was thus early about his heavenly Fathers buſineſs, can any man that hath his underſtanding, believe or think that ever he followed his ſuppoſed fathers calling, a Carpenter? And I would have ſuch men as are ſo earneſt againſt Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for Miniſters, and that ſay they ought to labour with their hands; to declare unto the World what outward trade,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118577:5"/>calling, or ſecular employment <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> had, or that he wrought with his hands to get a livelihood. What Scripture-proof they can produce; or that any one of the Apoſtles, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts, or Miniſters did work with their own hands, ſave <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> who did it of their own voluntary ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord? for they had neither precept nor command from Chriſt Jeſus ſo to do: for if they had, ſurely it would have been mentioned in Scripture. And (no doubt) had there been any, but that <hi>Paul</hi> would have charged <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> whom he calleth his ſons, and thoſe other Paſtors and Teachers of the Churches, <hi>whom he chargeth to feed the flock of Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> alſo to have laboured with their hands for a livelihood, had there been any ſuch precept or command. Nay, <hi>Paul</hi> doth evidently teſtifie the contrary in ſundry pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture, for he ſaith, he had power, and might have been chargeable, as well as other the Apoſtles of Chriſt. And let all men conſider, and read ſeriouſly what Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, and 14 <hi>Verſes;</hi> how many arguments doth the Apoſtle there uſe to prove that Miniſters ought to be maintained? as firſt, from the power that Chriſt hath given. Secondly, from warfare. Thirdly, from the planter of a Vineyard and feeder of a flock. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, from the Law of God. Fifthly, from Equity. Sixthly, from the example of thoſe that ſerved at the Altar. Seventh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe <hi>The Lord hath ordained, that they which preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi> Eighthly, from 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. <hi>They are called Ambaſſadours for Chriſt;</hi> and was it ever known but that Ambaſſadours and Souldiers were provided for? and doth not the ſame <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.8. ſay, <hi>I robbed other Churches, taking wages of them to do you ſervice?</hi> and 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.6. he ſaith, <hi>Nor of men ſought we glory, neither of you, nor yet of others, when we might have been burdenſome, as the Apoſtles of Chriſt.</hi> And I pray God that the ſame minde might be in thoſe men, who are ſo eager againſt all Maintenance for Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, that was in Saint <hi>Paul: Not to ſeek glory from men,</hi> nor their followers or admirers by ſo doing. And let theſe men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118577:5"/>what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Let him that is taught in the Word, communicate unto him that teacheth in all good things.</hi> Therefore I ſay to ſuch men as the Apoſtle in the next Verſe ſaith, <hi>Be not deceived, God is not mocked, nor will not be mocked. For whatſoever a man ſoweth, ſo ſhall he alſo reap:</hi> and 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.12, 13. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.18. For the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the Oxe that treadethout the corn;</hi> and <hi>The labourer is worthy of his reward:</hi> and <hi>Philip.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>I rejoyced greatly, that now at laſt your care for me hath flouriſhed again, wherein ye were alſo careful, but ye lacked opportunity:</hi> by all which above-ſaid, I am fully perſwaded, that it is the will of God the Father, and of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, Redeemer and Saviour, and of the Holy Ghoſt our Sanctifier, that the Miniſters and Preachers of the Goſpel ſhould be provided for with a competent means and allowance: whereby they may cheerfully perform the work of their Miniſtery and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling without grief of minde and ſpirit, or their working with their own hands for a livelihood: although Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> in his great book lately ſet forth againſt <hi>Infants-Baptiſme,</hi> the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery and Miniſters of all <hi>Chriſtendome, page</hi> 598. ſaith, You plead, That <hi>the mouth of the Ox muſt not be muzzled, that tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out the corn:</hi> that it is the will of God, that ſuch <hi>as preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel:</hi> I anſwer, it is moſt true, there is a power and liberty allowed for ſuch as ſerve the Church to eat and to drink and to ſubſiſt (in caſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſubſiſt otherwiſe) at the charges of the Church; but it is moſt commendable and thank-worthy in the Miniſtery to ſerve the Church and preach the Goſpel freely: and as far as it is poſſible not to be burthenſome in this kinde at all, as namely in caſe they have any eſtates of their own, or can im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove themſelves in any ſuch outward employment, labour, or lawful calling whereby to obtein a competent livelihood. And thus the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> and the firſt Miniſters of the Goſpel did, <hi>they laboured, working with their own hands,</hi> as oft as they could conveniently, and <hi>their own hands miniſtred to their own neceſſities,</hi> and they had ſome honeſt outward occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118577:6"/>as alſo Chriſt himſelf had, and followed too till he was wholly taken up in travel to preach the Truth. Therefore <hi>Mark.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Is not this the Carpenter?</hi>) wherein they wrought at all times, ſaving when they were actually employed in ſome ſervice of preaching to the World, writing, diſputing, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting, &amp;c. as is plain to him that conſults theſe Scriptures, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.3, 4, and 20.33, 34, 35. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.7. and 12.12, 13, 18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.11, 12. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 29. 2 <hi>Theſſ</hi> 3.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. Thus far Maſter <hi>Fiſher:</hi> To all which I briefly thus ſay, and hope that which is above written will ſatisfie all men whoſe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings are not blinded, and whoſe judgements are free and unprejudicated, doth not fully confute what Mr <hi>Fiſher</hi> hath there written, and likewiſe cited by me: and I muſt needs further ſay, that <hi>Mr. Fiſher</hi> did not do well for to leave out in his allegation of <hi>Mark</hi> 6.3. <hi>the Son of Mary:</hi> Shall I ſay he was blind &amp; did not ſee it? or that he did it wilfully to deceive his ſimple followers? I leave all men to judge as they pleaſe: for I am perſwaded that <hi>Mr. Fiſher</hi> knoweth full vvell, being ſo vvell acquainted with the Scriptures, as himſelf pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be, that thoſe ſpeeches and ſayings were onely uſed by ſuch as could not endure Chriſt his teaching and doctrine, thereby to diſgrace both him and it, as is plain in <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Mark</hi> in the Verſes before and after above-alledged. And may not I truly ſay, that ſome formerly, and that ſome men there were and are of latter times, even in our memories, that have ſpoken againſt the faithfulleſt and painfulleſt Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Preachers that have boldly reproved ſin, hoping thereby to draw men to repentance, have they not been ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed at and called, one the ſon of an Oatmeal-man, another the ſon of a Smith, another the ſon of a Carpenter; and by other names according to their fathers Trade or occupation, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to diſgrace them and their Miniſtery: now becauſe they were ſo called, did they therefore labour in their fathers cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling? ſurely no. Secondly, to his proofs out of the <hi>Acts,</hi> how doth it thereby appear, that <hi>Paul</hi> was either by precept or command to labour in ſome Trade or Occupation to get his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118577:6"/>living, more then the reſt of the Apoſtles or Diſciples? As for <hi>Mr. Fiſhers</hi> proofs out of the <hi>Corinth.</hi> examine his and mine, and approve of them which are moſt agreeing to the minde of the Spirit of God, and the practice of Chriſt Jeſus himſelf and of his Apoſtles, Diſciples and Miniſters, declared and ſet down in the New Teſtament. And for Mr. <hi>Fiſhers</hi> text 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.9. I deſire you to compare mine with his taken out of the ſame Chapter 6 Verſe, and that out of Chap. 5.12, 13. as alſo that out of 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.18. by all which places I hope it will cleerly appear that Miniſters ought to have maintenance. Now concerning Mr. <hi>Fiſhers</hi> laſt proof, <hi>viz.</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, Verſes: I ſay, that the Apoſtle there ſpeaketh not of Miniſters, but of ſuch that profeſſed themſelves to be Chriſtians, and yet would live idlely upon the Churches charge: if you will but duly read and conſider the ſaid Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Laſtly, I deſire all ſuch men as are ſo oppoſite againſt a Miniſtery or maintenance for Miniſters, to conſider ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with themſelves, what judgements the Lord in Scripture did not onely threaten, but brought upon thoſe places and perſons who have contemned his faithful Miniſters and Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, taking from them their maintenance which was due unto them from the Law and Goſpel, or ever did thoſe places and perſons enjoy peace and quietneſs from the Lord, till they repented, and till the Lords worſhip was firſt reſtored, and his Miniſters and meſſengers provided for: Let theſe men declare from Scripture, if they can; and may not ſuch men be termed worſe then <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> for he allowed a portion for the Prieſts of <hi>Egypt, Gen.</hi> 47.22. Neither did the Heathen Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs that ever I read of, ſuffer their Prieſts to labour for their livelihood, but allowed maintenance unto them: And will Chriſtians, profeſſing the glorious Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, labour to deprive his Miniſters and Meſſengers of maintenance, forcing them to labour for a livelihood? God forbid: but, I truſt, the Lord, by his Providence, hath raiſed up theſe men that now are the Supream Power of this
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118577:7"/>Common-weal, to perform the Lords will, for the ſetling of a competent maintenance for his Miniſters or Meſſengers, to the rejoycing, I hope, of the hearts of all that truly love and fear the Lord. And that they may ſo do, the good God of heaven and earth make them as ſo many <hi>Zerubbabels,</hi> and <hi>Nehemiahs,</hi> for the ſetting up of his worſhip in purity among us, and the upholding of pious, able, and godly Miniſters in the Common-weal, over which the Lord hath ſet them; that ſo not onely we, but our poſterities may bleſs and praiſe the Lord therefore: Now leaving what I have written to your ſelf, and all others that fear the Lord; and whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences are unbiaſſed to judge of what I have written. And if it be not according to truth, let them not approve of it; but if not, rather reprove it; <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my houſe</hi> 
                  <date> the <hi>11th. of the ſixth Moneth,</hi> 1653.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:118577:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
